<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exact history of the life of James Naylor with his parents, birth, education, profession, actions, &amp; blaspheemies [sic]. Also how he came first to be a Quaker, and received his commission from heaven (as he saith) when he was in the field at plow. Taken from his own mouth. With the doctrines, tenets and practises of some other of the same sect. / By John Deacon.</title>
            <author>Deacon, John, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82017</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D482</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E903_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207417</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866467</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866467</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118742</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82017)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118742)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 136:E903[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exact history of the life of James Naylor with his parents, birth, education, profession, actions, &amp; blaspheemies [sic]. Also how he came first to be a Quaker, and received his commission from heaven (as he saith) when he was in the field at plow. Taken from his own mouth. With the doctrines, tenets and practises of some other of the same sect. / By John Deacon.</title>
                  <author>Deacon, John, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 58 [i.e. 50] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edward Thomas, and are to be sold at his house in Green Arbor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Page 50 misnumbered 58.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "12 Febr."; the 7 in imprint date has been crossed out and date altered to 1656.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118742:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXACT HISTORY of the life of JAMES NAYLOR WITH HIS PARENTS, BIRTH, EDU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CATION, PROFESSION, ACTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONS, &amp; BLASPHEEMIES.</p>
            <p>ALSO How he came firſt to be a QUAKER, and received his commiſſion from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven (as he ſaith) when he was in the Field at Plow.</p>
            <p>Taken from his own mouth.</p>
            <p>With the Doctrines, Tenets and practiſes of ſome other of the ſame Sect.</p>
            <p>By JOHN DEACON.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Deut. 13.1, 2, 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>If there ariſe among you a Prophet, or a dreamer of dreams, and giveth thee a ſign or wonder: and the ſign come to paſſe, &amp;c. Thou ſhalt not hearken unto the words of that Prophet; for the Lord proveth you, to know whether you love the Lord your God with all your heart, and with all your ſoul</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſaiah 14.12, 13, 14, 15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>How art thou fallen from Heaven, O Lucifer? &amp;c. For thou haſt ſaid in thine heart, I will aſcend into Heaven, I will aſcend above the heights of the clouds, I will be like unto the moſt high. Yet thou ſhalt be brought down to Hell, to the ſides of the pit</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Theſ. 2.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Let no man deceive you by any means, for that day ſhall not come, except there come a falling away firſt, and that man of ſin be revealed. the ſon of perdition</p>
            </q>
            <p>London, <hi>Printed for</hi> Edward Thomas, <hi>and are to be ſold at his houſe in</hi> Green Arbor, 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118742:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118742:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I ſuppoſe thee ſenſible of that which I may well call a ſound principle, as that the ſupreme and beſt end of all things is Gods glory; firſt and next our own hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, into which ocean we ought to empty and pour forth all our deſires, actions and abilities, that ſo we may injoy Gods moſt comfortable bleſſing here, with the fruition thereof (eternal life) hereafter; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in every undertaking, with <hi>Moſes,</hi> I eſteeme it a ſignall evidence not only of reall wit, but a ſtep hire of true wiſedome, ſeriously to weigh and conſider what the end may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce; which (Courteous Reader) hath not been the leaſt of my care in this preſent under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking; for truth being an atribute of God, and love the like. I think to defend the firſt, and demonſtrate the other, cannot but tend to what hath been ſaid; and I dare pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume that in this one undertaking (if you read with a ſingle eye) you will find them both performed, truth defended by preventing
<pb facs="tcp:118742:3"/>
falſhoods and untrue reports, and love de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated by perverting thoſe that would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the inquiſitive, which it's probable the covetous may attempt not with an intent to ſatisfie the Reader, but his own unſatisfied purſe.</p>
            <p>I muſt needs confeſſe the trouble in colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting, this relation hath been great, and the paines no leſſe, which I might have avoided, but then have left thee perhaps either miſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, or elſe not at all acquainted with thoſe unheard of miſdemeanors.</p>
            <p>And if any ſhall ſuppoſe that becauſe I have heretofore had controverſie both by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute and in Print with the ſaid <hi>James Nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor,</hi> and that therefore what I have written may be rather out of envy to the man, then love to the truth: I aſſure him to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, for what I have done was and is only in diſcharge of that duty I ſuppoſe lies on every Chriſtian, to communicate that which may be beneficial to others, which he knows himſelf; as this muſt needs be which alſo will evidently witneſs, what with ſome cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions I have heretofore ſaid in their Society, that I feared (and now am ſure of it) that
<pb facs="tcp:118742:3"/>
if all the errors and blaſphemies that have been either forged or upheld by any or all the archeſt Hereticks ſince the death of our Saviour were buried in irreviveable obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion, they might be equalled if not exupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in them and their opinions, as the inſuing diſcourſe will demonſtrate.</p>
            <p>I have been plain becauſe I would be brief, and brief becauſe the occaſion required it; and have ſaid nothing but for what I have an evidence either one way or other: ſo that you need not miſtruſt the certainty, but rather ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the abſurdity of his actions, of whom thou haſt here, <hi>Firſt, a true Relation of his birth &amp; education; next the manner how he was ſeduced; after that a true Narrative of what hath been remarkable ſince that time, either for action or opinion, with an exact relation of their Principles and Tenets, and then laſtly, ſome very choice ſtories of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their Sect:</hi> All which may ſerve to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with the truth that they are erronious: which that we may all ſee ſo as to avoid, and in avoiding them imbrace that truth, and poſſeſſe that grace which will aſſuredly
<pb facs="tcp:118742:4"/>
conduct us ſafely to an eternall habitation, is and ſhall be the deſires and moſt affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate wiſhes of</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my lodging at</hi> Bun-hill London, <date>Decemb. <hi>the 30th. 1656.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your aſſured Friend in what he can, JOHN DEACON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118742:4"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An exact Hiſtory of the Life and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>James Naylor</hi> ſince he became a <hi>Quaker.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Eſus Chriſt the only reall and eternal Son of the Almighty Father, that out of a fore-ſeeing and fore knowing ſenſe (of the ſtate of all things) in himſelf fore-ſaw and underſtood that the inſtable and mutable mind of miſerable man would be always buſied and imployed upon one ſubject or another, eſteemed it a part of that true wiſedome inherent in himſelf, preſcribed ſuch a matter for it to work on, as might tend principally to their own perpetual good, and his eternal glory. <hi>Seek ye firſt the Kingdom of God,</hi> (and then that they might reap no diſcouragement by the want of meaner injoyments, as riches and honour, he promiſeth a taſte of that here (his bleſſings) which in a higher ſenſe ſhall be wholy injoyed hereafter) <hi>and all theſe things ſhall be added unto you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to attain any happineſſe or precious injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is to be purchaſed by the overcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of withholding difficulties; we muſt firſt indeavour to remove all defects and impediments
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118742:5"/>
as evill which is contrary and oppoſite to good; and the readieſt way ſo to do is to underſtand and know the cauſe that may either withhold us from the omiſſion of duty, or incourage us to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of diſobedience, that ſo that being known we may be the better fortified to withſtand any temptation from them proceeding that providence ſhould ſuffer to aſſault us, which is the intent and ſubſtance of this precedent diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>Sad it is to conſider, that as the world draws neer to a period, the wickedneſſe of men innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates; and that every day Which ſets them a ſtep neerer to death, ſhould throw them a ſtride fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from a better life: as if every Age were only an addition of impiety, and a new torrent of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, which added a ſtream more to the complea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the fulneſſe of ſuch ſins as might extract an immediate deſtruction, as not only bare reports, but to ſad experience verifies in every Age, but more eſpecially in this wherein we live: not only Satan indeavouring to transfigure himſelf into an Angel of light; but man attempts to transform himſelf into an impe and angel of darkneſſe, in that a wretched and ſinful man ſhall be no more called <hi>James</hi> but (<hi>Jezebel</hi> for inchantment, and not) <hi>Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I come to what I intend, God in his juſtice have given over men at this time to yield ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the alurements of Satan, and to believe lies becauſe they have pleaſure in unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp;c. Among which number chiefly is one who for his horrid blaſphemies, is unworthy to be what he ſeems, a man who is well known by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118742:5"/>
the name of <hi>James Naylor,</hi> of whom 'tis hard to ſay whether he is moſt indued with wit or wickedneſſe; but it's eaſie to ſuppoſe; it were well for him he had none of the firſt, ſo he were void of the latter. But ſince Providence offereth ſo ſad a ſubject, I can do no leſſe in duty but lay forth my ſelf and my abilities in a caſe of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, when a man ſhall aſſume the name of God, and take unto himſelf his attributes, as doth this grand Seducer of whom I now intend to treat: and ſince ſome have worthily written of his Tryal and Examination, &amp;c. I ſhall not go about to erect any thing that may ſavour of Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tology, but carefully, truly and impartially, treat of what he hath done and practiced ſince he came to be a Quaker; that ſo by his miſcarriages the induſtrious may be improved, &amp; the drowſie awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened to underſtand the deceits of, and arme him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf againſt the man of ſin and his factors; and that I may ſo do I ſhall methodically proceed.</p>
               <p>Firſt, To decide that which various reports ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der diſputable to moſt, when indeed what is ſaid ſeems to be raiſed by ſuch as would willingly ſay ſomething, yet know not well what, which ſavours rather of a buſie-brain, then a well grounded knowledge; I mean his Parents, birth and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>He is the ſon of one Goodman <hi>Naylor</hi> (ſo called in the Country) of <hi>Anderſlow</hi> in the County of <hi>York,</hi> where he was born, neither to much plenty or mean penury; but as he was not over-rich, ſo was he not over-poor; but ſuch was his eſtate, that with his own induſtry (by report) he might
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118742:6"/>
have lived comfortably, as other Countrey people do whoſe hands are the Tenants that produce a livelihood. Concerning his profeſſion, reports are various, ſome ſay he was a Gentleman born and bred, others that he followed huſbandry; and ſome ſay this, and others that, but to ſatisfie the induſtrious, I ſhall in few words declare what I can a vouch to be truth if man may be believed; a Gentleman, now one of that honourable Society of <hi>Grayes Inn,</hi> who was either born or bred (if not both) either in or neer the ſame Town or place where this falſe prophet had his entrance into this tranſitory world, who was alſo School fellow with this <hi>Naylor,</hi> and knew his friends, reported to a friend of mine, before ſufficient witneſſe, that this <hi>James Naylor</hi> was the ſon of one Goodman <hi>Naylor</hi> (ſo called in the Country) by profeſſion a Sow-gelder, and did alſo follow the ſame profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Sow-gelder, and thereof made either all, or part of his livelihood (which was alſo reported by one that was a fellow Souldier with him in the Army) till ſuch time as he took up Armes and ſerved in the Army, firſt under the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> next under the Lord <hi>Lambert.</hi> And for his education it was neither ſuch as might indue him with more then to underſtand, write well, &amp; read his mother tongue; nor leſſe then might make him capable to undergo any ordinary imployment; and though he be a man of an exceeding quick wit, and ſharp ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, inriched with that commendable gift of good oritory with a very delightable melody in his utterance; yet he either out of policy or neglect, indeavours to make the world believe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118742:6"/>
he hath not at all bettered or improved it; for in his anſwer to my <hi>Publique Diſcovery,</hi> he ſeems to be ignorant what the word etimoliger means in that; when for his indeavouring to derive the word Trinity from <hi>Rome,</hi> in reply to that I call him deceitful Sophiſter, yet ſimple etimoliger; and in his anſwer to that Reply, he ſaith, here I am called a Soffiſter and an etimoliger, as if the word were odious, or had ſome relation to a ſcandalous or reviling ſtyle; but it is freely confeſſed that in another book, which he owneth, though perhaps ſome Jeſuit writ it; being an anſwer to Mr. <hi>Joſhua Miller</hi>'s <hi>Antichriſt in Man, the Quaking Idol.</hi> He there flies from what he pretends, immediate reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, to the rules of art &amp; learning, indeavouring to confute logical Silogiſms by the like, and that not only by ſuch as bear only the name, but alſo the exact rules according to art, though void of the power, becauſe they want the force of truth; ſo that I find he can write a very legible hand, (if that he writ to me was his own) he ſpells good Engliſh; and either he hath more in him then he will make known, (and then perhaps he is what I judge him to be, a Jeſuit) or elſe ſome other writes what he owns. In the next place it will be neceſſary to declare his original call and entrance into this damnable hereſie wherein he now ſtands, not as various reports render it, but as he himſelf hath often declared it, not only in private, but in the publique meeting at the Mouth within Alderſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, <hi>London,</hi> to me and many others that have had diſcourſe with him there.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118742:7"/>
               <head>The manner of his call and entrance into this damnable Sect and Hereſie wherein be now ſtands.</head>
               <p>HE ſaid, As I was in the Field at Plow, in Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley-ſeed time, meditating on the things of God, (in his apprehenſion) ſuddenly I heard a voice ſaying unto me, Get thee out from thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe, and from thy kindred, and I will be with thee at all times, and in all places. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I exceedingly rejoyced, that I had heard the voice of that God whom from a child I had indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to ſerve in ſincerity and uprightneſſe of heart, and whom before that time I had never Known in truth: So I went home and waited there a good while, and not being obedient to that heavenly call, I was caſt down and remained in a ſad condition, as many friends can witneſſe, who wondred to ſee ſuch a change in me, and thought I was diſtracted, and that the hand of God upon me had made me lunatick by deſtruction of my ſenſes, &amp; I would never have ſpoken nor eaten more: but after I was mad, and willing to go, I gave my eſtate away, and I began to make ſome proviſion, as Money, Apparel, and other neceſſaries for my journey; but a while afterwards going with a friend from my own houſe on ſome buſineſſe, having an old ſuit on, without any money, the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118742:7"/>
voice ſpake again, commanding me to go into the Weſt, and then it ſhould be revealed to me what was appointed for me to do; and not knowing whither I ſhould go, or what was appointed for me to do, neither having taken my leave of her whom the world calls my Wife, and thoſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren which according to the fleſh are mine, I was obedient, and after I had been there a while, it was given me what I ſhould declare; and ever ſince I have been obedient to that which is pure in me and in you all, Chriſt manifeſt in mortal fleſh.</p>
               <p>Whereupon I asked him whether that friend or any elſe beſides himſelf heard that ſame voice? or how ſhould it be known to be a truth, ſince we had nothing but his own word for it? He anſwered it was not a carnal audible voice, to be heard with an earthly ear, for it was heavenly; and that it is true, <hi>the ſpirit beaereth witneſſe, and I know his witneſſe is true.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>I asked him whether the voice were external or internal, and to whom he gave his eſtate?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He ſaid that that which is pure in all your conſciences, which convinces you of the evil you do, Chriſt in you, the true light ſpoke to that of God in me, and I heard it, and will witneſſe to that of God in you all (or words to this purpoſe) that it is pure and eternal.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>I asked him to whom he gave his goods and eſtate?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He ſaid to his Wife and children.</p>
               <p>When indeed I had thought in imitation of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118742:8"/>
Phariſees, he had boaſted of ſome deeds of charity he had done with it before men, not but that it was well beſtowed as it was diſpoſed of; for I think as they had moſt need of it, ſo they had moſt right to it; and the promiſe he faith, is fulfilled in that God hath witneſſed to his doctrine; but what that Witneſs, what that Power, and what that voice is, and from whence is evident.</p>
               <p>Firſt, By his Apoſtacy, in that when he had aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociated himſelf with a people that endeavoured to live and walk with and in the Lord, that he ſhould backſlide from thoſe ways of truth and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace ſuch errors as have led him unto the height of blaſphemy: when as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>They</hi> (and ſo he) <hi>went forth from us, because they were not of us:</hi> but like tares among Wheat diſagreeable and fit for nothing but Deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Secondly, By his Actions, the firſt ſtep whereof led him to ſuch art Act as gives much ſuſpition, nay even aſſurance of inconſtancy and adulteries, &amp;c. as hereafter ſhall be made evident in this diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, His Doctrine, in that he preacheth down all truth and up all errors, as denying either Magiſtracy or Miniſtry; or either Goſpel or civil Laws, or Diſcipline, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, By his Blaſphemies of which he is juſtly convicted (and for which he hath partly ſuffered) by the Supreme Authority; <hi>as that he is the Son of God, and the Son of God is but one;</hi> and then he being one, and the Son of God as (he ſaith) there is by that account no other: and queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118742:8"/>
he hath been long of this judgement though not ſo publique in it: For long ſince he ſaid, he was as holy: juſt and good as God himſelf, thereby claiming anequality with God though at a farther diſtance then now; for then he onely claimed an equality by purity, but now by dignity &amp; affinity, as being the Son of God, and one with the Father: See Mr. <hi>Farmer</hi>'s <hi>Satan inthron'd in his Chair of Peſtilence &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have firſt laid down thoſe four Heads as a ground-work to what I intend to enlarge upon in proſecution of this Treatiſe; but before I proceed to doe ſo, I ſhall ſpeak a word or two concerning the proceeding of the Supreme Authority againſt him of whom we now treat; by reaſon that many though ſome indiſcreetly ſay, The ſentence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt him ſavours of a harſh judgment thereby endeavouring to ſcandalize the ſupreme and high Authority with cruelty: to which I ſhall ſpeak a word or two impartially.</p>
               <p>Since it is eſteemed not onely in this, but in all other Nations, an act of high in juſtice to ſentence him to die the very worſt of deaths, that ſhall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume unto himſelf the title of his Prince or Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; or that ſhall any waies endeavour to impair the titles and glory of him : how much more ought he to die or ſuffer a worſe puniſhment that ſhall commit a greater offence, and make himſelf <hi>the Son of God, the King of righteouſneſſe.</hi> I have read of them that for bearing in their Coats of Arms that which belonged onely to the Crowne have ſuffered as Traytors; as Lord <hi>Howard</hi> Duke
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118742:9"/>
of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> with his ſon the Earle of <hi>Surrey,</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th. though men in great and high eſteem and of no leſs honour, for this offence and no other were arraigned, convicted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned as Traytors: then how much more ought he that ſhall make himſelf <hi>the Son of God, &amp;c.</hi> to die if it were poſſible a hundred times? for look how much God is above man, ſo much ought he to ſuffer a juſt torment more then death if it were poſſible; And therefore the ſentence which was paſt upon him, and he hath partly undergone, was more in mercy then juſtice could well admit, and they with honour pronounce againſt him: but 'tis true indeed, mercy ſhall find mercy, and its a ſignal token of a tender charity in that mercy was exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the midſt of juſt Judgement.</p>
               <p>I ſhall now proceed to treat upon and examine the ſeveral things before laid down.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That it is an evidence that that voice, that power, and that witneſſe is not of God or good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that ſpoke to him, goeth with him, and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth of him. Firft, by reaſon of his apoſtacy; it is a precept in the word of God, concerning him which backſlideth from the faith which ſtands in Jeſus Chriſt the onely reall and eternal Son of God the Father, after the firſt and ſecond admonition, if he repent not, give (ſaith the holy Ghoſt) or deliver ſuch a man over to Satan, which is, excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, or exclude him; ſo then he being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered over to Satan is no more of God, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect that power which is given to the Church to excommuninate falſe members, hath been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118742:9"/>
on him as a backſliding brother; we ought to look on him as one under the power of Satan, and not to bid him <hi>good ſpeed,</hi> leſt we be partakers with him in his evill deeds: And indeed if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider him in the ſtate of a falne brother, we cannot wonder to ſee him raign in all manner of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in reſpect the Holy Ghoſt ſaith, <hi>that falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets mnſt come, and falſe Chriſts ſhall ariſe:</hi> it is juſt with God to give him over to <hi>believe lies,</hi> becauſe he hath pleaſure in <hi>unrighteouſneſs;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2 10, 11, 12. 1 John 4.8. Heb. 12.29.</note> For as God is light, and ſo able to diſcern all things; ſo is he all-ſufficient to underſtand and do all things: and as he is all love to his children; ſo is he all judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (yet merciful) to his enemies: Therefore let him repent him of and not perſevere in his blaſphemies;<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.23.</note> for though he can contemn Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and ſay in the mind he is in, he would not be uncovered though he were in the Parliament houſe: Yet let him know, that <hi>he that reſiſteth</hi> (or contemneth) <hi>the Powers, reſiſteth the Ordinances of God: and he that reſiſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See Mr.Bourn, p. 41.</note> 
                  <hi>receiveth unto himſelf dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation:</hi> And it is a moſt ſad thing indeed with <hi>Korah, Dathan, and Abiram</hi> to play with and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn the wrath of God-leſt the bowels of the earth chaſtiſe their preſumption.<note place="margin">Rom. 13.2, 3.</note> I both would and ſhall endeavour brevity in what convenience may require; yet for the good of thoſe that ſtand between two not knowing whether they were better to backſlide or ſtand faſt where they are: I ſhall endeavour in a few words to ſhew you what I apprehend to be the cauſe of the Lords for ſaking him, and giving him over tp his own luſt: and as I
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118742:10"/>
often told him and <hi>George Fox, Borows</hi> and <hi>Hober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorn,</hi> &amp;c. I obſerved a Learned Author laid this down as <hi>maxim</hi> in Divinity, <hi>that when a man ceaſes</hi> (with this quaking Sect) <hi>to be guided by Gods Laws, God gives him over to be ruled by his own luſts;</hi> and therefore I wiſhed them not to whet and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the anger of the Lord which is a <hi>conſuming fire:</hi> And in a word, I am cleerly of this opinion, that had he had true faith, he could never have finally fallen to reprobation and blaſphemie: It is probable he might have faith, but not true faith; for as ſaith Dr. <hi>Holmes, there is a faith of adherance, and there is a faith of aſſurance, &amp;c.</hi> The true faith muſt be exerciſed in true worſhip, the end where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is true happineſs, and all worſhip not agreeing with Gods revealed will, is prophaneſs and irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, the end whereof is not happy but wretched; <hi>For this is life eternal to know God, and whom he hath ſent Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and (not <hi>James Naylor.</hi>) And he that expects to reign with nim, muſt believe that he is able to ſave to the uttermoſt;<note place="margin">Heb. 11.6. John 1.11. 2 Cor. 5.7. John 20 29. Heb. 11.1. Epheſ. 2.8.</note> and all other that pretend ſo to doe beſides him are ſeducers; and let him pretend what revelations he will, this a true believer muſt know and relye on, <hi>That no man hath ſeen Gods eſſence, that is greater then any finite apprehenſion;</hi> ſo that let <hi>Quakers</hi> and their ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing teachers ſay what they pleaſe; this is truth and no lie, <hi>we walk by faith</hi> (the eye of the ſoul) <hi>and not by ſight;</hi> and therefore Chriſt when he had aſſumed a viſible nature (in his incarnation) for that work of our Redemption would not be long converſant on earth in his publique Miniſtry, that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118742:10"/>
our ſalvations might not be in ſenſe, but believing; <hi>bleſſed are they that have not ſeen yet have believed.</hi> The neceſſity of faith appears in that, <hi>the juſt ſhall live by it: by faith we are juſtified,</hi> without it <hi>we cannot pleaſe God;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Habakkuk 2.4.</note> 
                  <hi>and what is not of faith is ſin:</hi> the excellency of it in that it apprehendeth the riches of Chriſt, and in him the unſpeakable treaſure of Gods mercy, peace of conſcience, reconcilation with God, remiſſion of ſin, indemptnity from the guilt and puniſhment, &amp;c. In <hi>fine</hi> all things which concur to the compleating true happineſs. It ſtiled <hi>Abraham</hi> Gods friend, and us his ſons; it is the ſanctuary of a troubled ſpirit the firſt fruits of the heavenly Paradiſe: In a word, precious is that faith which believeth all the word of God is true and to be obeyed, and ſaith, that <hi>Jeſus</hi> (and not <hi>James</hi>) <hi>is the true Chriſt: and that there is Salvation in no other name under Heaven.</hi> They beſt know how ſweet a Jewel faith is, that can value the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment by the want of it: but to ſuch as <hi>Naylor</hi> and his ſect, who are deluded with falſe light and temptations of ſecurity, there appeareth no want of it in themſelves, becauſe they are ſecure: but I heartily wiſh they knew, and would believe there is a common faith, which reprobates may have, and that is either hiſtorical ſuch at the Divels have, <hi>Jam. 2.19.</hi> or temporal, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.20. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.13. and this is either a faith of miracles, or a deluſion of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity. There be many degrees, but one onely object of true and ſaving faith, and that is <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> (and not <hi>James Naylor,</hi>) and that which we are to believe and obey, is the infallible truth of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118742:11"/>
God (the firſt, God, the ſecond, his Oracles.) and his Will concerning our Salvation revealed in his Word. The word and teſtimony of man may be the ground of opinion which is of things probable; but true faith can ſtand on no other <hi>baſis</hi> but the Word of God which is infallible, certain and can have no falſhood in it, and he that goeth without this guide runneth like thoſe <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to the mountains of the <hi>Cananites,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Numb. 14 40.</note> to their own deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as this Sect, and particularly him of whom we now ſpeak, gives too ſad a teſtimony of this truth.</p>
               <p>I deſire thy excuſe (Courteous Reader) if I have been tranſported too far on this Subject, be thou pleaſed to read it but with as much patience as I writ it, and 'twill extenuate the Teadiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it; I ſhall reſt no longer here, but preſſe onward to what I intend, and that leads me to the ſecond ground, which argues the ſpirit by which he is acted to be not divine but diabolical. Which is this,</p>
               <p>Secondly, By his actions in general, but chiefly by reaſon that the firſt ſtep he took after his apoſtacy gives ſtrong ſuſpicion, nay plain aſſurance that he is guilty of inconſtancy and adultery, to the clearing of which I ſhall proceed, and in ſo doing it will be requiſite to trace him along from the beginning, when he firſt left that Church whereof he was a member; and in ſo doing obſerve what is worth the noting, as ſhall ſeem moſt conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Naylor</hi> being a member of a Congregation at
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118742:11"/>
                  <hi>Wool-Church</hi> in <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> he was there excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated for his blaſphemous Tenets, as Mr. <hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher Marſhall</hi> Paſtor of that Church whereof he was a member confeſſed; <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> who is alſo well known to be an able, godly and ſincere Miniſter of the Word of God; who alſo in a Letter to a friend, a Copy whereof I read, is related this ſtory, that <hi>James Naylor,</hi> ſince he was a <hi>Quaker,</hi> having gotten into the acquaintance of a woman named Miſtris <hi>Roper,</hi> and her huſband being gone away from her on ſome occaſion a long voyage; he the ſaid <hi>James Naylor</hi> uſed greatly to frequent her company, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more then ordinarily, and to be plain, more then civily familiar with her, uſing frequently to dandle her on his knee, imbracing and kiſſing her more then was either fitting or beſeeming civility; and in the time of her buſbands abſence, either by ſome other, or (as is moſt likely) and is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by <hi>James Naylor</hi> ſhe was gotten with child, and when her huſband had been abſent from her, and <hi>Naylor</hi> acquainted with her ſeven and forty weeks, ſhe was brought to bed of a Baſtard-child; and this was ſeveral times profered by my ſelf and my loving friend Mr. <hi>Perſival,</hi> to be proved and made good before any Magiſtrate, if they durſt put it to tryal; and I profered to read the Letter, or at leaſt a Copy of it, at their publique meeting, provided that <hi>Naylor</hi> or any other ſhould but ingage that I ſhould have neither violence offered to me nor to the paper, but it would not be granted; and <hi>Naylor</hi> himſelf when accuſed with it in his meeting, was unable to clear himſelf any
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118742:12"/>
further then with ſilence, which gives conſent, <note place="margin">A weak ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe (yet as ſtrong as his innocenſe.)</note>and leaving his ſtanding he ſaid, <hi>This is a prieſt lie.</hi> And without queſtion had he been able to have ſaid any thing that might have ſavoured of an excuſe, he would have been ready to have ſpoke that with much addition, his tongue being free to run commonly, not only beyond reaſon, but truth also; and one paſſage in the ſaid Letter muſt not be omitted; which was,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Naylor</hi> being on a time in private with her, the ſaid Miſtris <hi>Roper,</hi> dandling, imbracing and kiſſing her laſciviouſly, ſhe in a jeſting manner thus expreſt her ſelf, as glorying in their ſtolen wickdneſs, <hi>Now</hi> James, <hi>what would the world ſay ſhould they ſee thee and I in this poſture?</hi> but what his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwer was I cannot ſay, but it may eaſily be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be ſuch as ſhould incourage her in her ſin with greater impudency, if it might be; and though he nor his friends durſt not bring it to the Bar of juſtice, he knowing his own guilt, and fearing the puniſhment on the Law in that caſe provided: yet Providence hath ſo diſpoſed of that buſineſſe, that ſince he was in queſtion for that horrid and ſcarce to be paralel'd blaſphemy, it hath been a matter diſputed of before the Seat of Juſtice; for Mr.<hi>Perſival,</hi> our a zeal to Piety, by having impiety corrected, went to the Honourable <hi>Bramfield,</hi> a known godly pious Gentleman, and Churchman of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee choſen to examine his miſdemeanors, and gave him to underſtand the matter, and told him, that if his Honour pleaſed to ſend for Mr.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118742:12"/>
                  <hi>Lamb</hi> at <hi>Elie-Houſe,</hi> he had in his cuſtody the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Copy of the Letter, containing the whole proceedings before the ſaid Church, under Mr. <hi>Marſhall</hi>'s own hand: Which Mr.<hi>Lamb</hi> being ſent for, and producing the ſaid Papers, they were read to the ſaid <hi>Naylor</hi>'s face in the open Court; who being asked what he could ſay for himſelf? as to this did not nor indeed could not deny the action, but only denied the time, as being not ſince he was a Quaker, but when he was a Souldier; and he ſaid it was not in that nature in which thoſe Letters preſented it, as in any diſhoneſt or laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious way, but only he then kiſs'd her in the way of courtſhip. To which, anſwer was returned that it was no ſuch thing as he pretended, but ſince he was a profeſſed Quaker, and not before; which when he ſee it would be made ſo evident, that it would be rendered inexcuſable, he was ſilent as to that; and that it is ſo by conſequence, hereafter ſhall be verified. Thus much for this particular act, I ſhall now come to treat of ſome of his actions in general.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:118742:13"/>
               <head>Here followeth a brief Narrative of ſome Actions committed by him, with ſeverall other Paſſages of the like nature, ſince, and not before he was a <hi>Quaker.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>JAmes Naylor</hi> being on a time in a meeting at <hi>Sedbergh</hi> in the <hi>North,</hi> peremptarily aſked one who is reputed to bean honeſt ſincere Chriſtian, named <hi>Samuel Handley,</hi> whether he were free from ſinne or no? who replied, he was ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of his own infirmities, and therefore a ſinner; with that <hi>Naylor</hi> railed at him with the uncivil terms of Thief and Murtherer, <hi>Cane</hi> and the like; and juſtified himſelf to be perfectly free from ſin: And here may I fitly inſert a paſſage between one (whoſe name I omit, because he is well known about where he lives) and my ſelfe at the Bull and Mouth within Alderſgate.</p>
               <p>I being on a time at the ſaid meeting, fell by chance in diſcourſe with one who (by his ſignal termes as <hi>thou</hi> and <hi>thee</hi>) I ſuppoſed to be a <hi>Quaker,</hi> with whom (after other things) I had ſome ſpeech concerning preſent and perfect perfection, which he in part denying, I ſaid that <hi>Naylor</hi> owned, and preached to maintain it, as in a Letter extant, in the <hi>Quakers whiteſt Divel unvailed;</hi> whereupon the aforeſaid <hi>A.A.</hi> called me lyer, and child of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118742:13"/>
divel, till producing the book it ſelfe I read unto him <hi>Naylors</hi> own words; which when he heard, he ſaid, doth <hi>James</hi> ſay ſo? I anſwered, yes; nay then ſaid <hi>he, It is truth.</hi> So far are they bewitched with his deluſion, as to ſteer their faith by his unſtable and vitiated brain.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Naylor</hi> hearing of a Bull-baiting in <hi>Cheſterfield,</hi> whereof Mr.<hi>Billingsly</hi> was Paſtor, he writ a Letter to the ſaid known godly Miniſter, wherein he ſaid that ſwearing, curſing, bulbaiting, and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of God was the fruits of <hi>John Billingſly</hi>'s Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry; thereby indeavouring to ſcandalize the man that had done him no prejudice;<note place="margin">See Learned &amp; Reverend Mr. <hi>Bourn's defence of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> p. 17. 18.</note> which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed was his uſual practice, as is evident in many particulars too tedious to name; which is a ſignal demonſtration ofa malicious ſpirit: but when he was in publique, he was accuſed with this act of falſhood (indeed the proper fruits of his ſpirit) he denied it, calling him lyer that laid it to his charge, till his Letter was produced, which proved him in an untruth, when he wanted not impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to excuſe (but grace to repent for) that ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accuſation.</p>
               <p>A Poor honeſt Country-man of <hi>Wingerworth</hi> in the County of <hi>Derby,</hi> having heard <hi>Naylor</hi> prate after his uſual manner (error and blaſphemy) was ſo infuſed (not with pure light as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend) but with a deſperate diveliſh humour, that he deſtroyed and drowned himſelf; which plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeaks by what power and ſpirit they are acted: Not unlike to this was that of <hi>Mary White,</hi> who
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118742:14"/>
by the damnable ſedition of <hi>Burrows, Howgall,</hi> and <hi>Hoberthorn,</hi> the orators for the promotion of the <hi>man of ſin</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>James Naylor</hi> (not the) but their Chriſt.</note> and his cauſe, was miſerably be witched and inchanted to death after ſeveral and ſad mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and fits, as heaving and ſtrugling like Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſion fits, with ſtrange out-cries, as barking like a Dog, lowing like a Cow, &amp;c. witneſſed by <hi>Bartholomew Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ald,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See a ſheet called <hi>quakers or enchanters</hi> Sold by Mr. Dod</note> 
                  <hi>Suſannah Green,</hi> and <hi>William White</hi> on oath before <hi>Edmund Harvey, <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
                  </hi> And the like that of <hi>Gilpine</hi> and alſo <hi>Cotton Croſland</hi> that hanged himſelfe, who pretended he knew more and higher things himſelf them any or all the Miniſters in <hi>England</hi> did; the truth whereof the end demonſtrates. And another in the <hi>North,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See <hi>Gilpin</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end.</note> whoſe name I think was <hi>Birch,</hi> who was ſeen in the act committing Buggery with a mare, and for it fled, all then profeſſed <hi>Quakers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It were in vain to cite every ſlight paſſage, and to treat upon his ſeveral lies and falſhoods wich would rather afford a great volume, then be contained in ſo ſmall a tract as this Treatiſe: and although much more might be ſaid to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, I only intended to touch on this by the way, and come to the next thing intended to be treated on, as an evidence that he is under a ſpirit of error.</p>
               <p>The third evidence is his Doctrine, in that he preacheth down all truth, and up all error, &amp;c. and here I ſhall begin with that which is moſt mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial to this ſubject.<note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Bourn, his defence of the Scriptures,</hi> 9. 20.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And firſt, In that he ſaith he is as holy, juſt and good as God himſelf, without either limitation
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118742:14"/>
or reſervation; as was witneſſed by two at <hi>Kendal,</hi> and an honeſt Inhabitant of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderborow</hi> neer to <hi>Kendal:</hi> Saith, he and many others heard him utter this blaſphemy, but being all followers of <hi>Naylor</hi> he believes they will be ſlow and unwilling to teſtifie the truth in this caſe: yet he calls me lier often for accuſing him for holding perfect perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when by this account, if he were as holy, juſt &amp; good as God himſelf,<note place="margin">See my Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique diſcoverie of their ſecret deceit.</note> and not perfect, what then? is God imperfect? O horrid blaſphemy! He holds that the Scriptures are not the word of God, but only a declaration of that word; and that their words and Letters are the declaration alſo; ſo then both being one in quality, equality afordeth no different diſtinction: &amp; ſome of them have burned the Bible (as I have heard them boaſt) in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of it. And <hi>Naylor</hi> hath ſaid more then once that he that expected to be ſaved by that Jeſus Chriſt that died at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived;<note place="margin">See <hi>the perfect Phariſee. p.</hi> 8.</note> and this character the holy Ghoſt gives of the man of ſin, antichriſt;<note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Boure, p.</hi> 16.</note> if any man (as <hi>Naylor</hi> in effect) denies Chriſt as being come in the fleſh that is a deceiver and an antichriſt;<note place="margin">1 John 2.22.23.</note> he hath alſo erroneouſly taught that we owe no obedience to any Magiſtrates, or to render them any honour or ſubjection, which though in publique he deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before the vulgar people, yet then was he teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to be in a lie by one of his own Sect, who openly confeſſed he received that doctrine from <hi>Naylor</hi> himſelf, ſee the <hi>Northern Relation,</hi> p. 9. and oftentimes he hath denied that the Scriptures and written word of God to be either the judge of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118742:15"/>
ſpirits or of controverſies, or the rule by which every Chriſtian ought to walk, and by which he ought to guide himſelf and limit his actions; and when I ſaid I did underſtand a diſtinct and vaſt difference between Chriſt the word, and the word of Chriſt, the firſt being God, the other but the expreſſive temporal word of God,<note place="margin">See my <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique diſcovery.</hi>
                  </note> wherein, the holy Ghoſt ſtooping to our infirmities ſpeaks in ſuch termes as may impreſſe on our capacities. I defie your diſtinctions and your carnal words, for Chriſt is the word, and God is the word, and all other words are without in the nature, &amp;c. He alſo affirmed in his anſwers to my queries (extant in my <hi>Publique Diſcovery</hi>) that that immortality, that incorruption, &amp;c. ſpoken of us injoyed by Saints in Heaven, he injoyed here immediately on earth; and that in oppoſing him and his hereſie, I ſought and indeavoured to kill the juſt one in them, and that I would murder them that were out of <hi>Cains</hi> way and were tranſplanted from death to life, with much more of the like abſurd ſtuff. And on a time being diſputing with a godly able Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, about that light in all men, <hi>Naylor</hi> laid down this abſurd error, <hi>That an Indian that never heard nor read of Chriſt, by that which is in every man, knew Chriſt Jeſus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See the <hi>defence of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures p.</hi> p. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>as well as any man.</hi> It will not be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent in this place to inſert one notable ſtory of him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:118742:15"/>
               <head>A very notable Story worth your Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and unqueſtionably true.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>JAmes Naylor</hi> being on a time at a place where it ſo fel out that a godly Miniſter* chanced to be at the ſame time who ſtood up &amp; ſaid unto him,<note place="margin">One Mr. <hi>Cole</hi> a known godly Miniſter.</note> the Lord put it upon my ſpirit to ſpeak a few words unto him on ſome things that might tend to edifie the audience: to which <hi>Naylor</hi> audaciouſly and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptiouſly ſaid, (as making it a matter admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) <hi>haſt thou received a meſſage from the Lord, and I not know of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> thereby pretending privacy to and knowledge of the hidden ſecrets and unſearchable councels of the Lord, like to <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15. <hi>Which way went the Spirit of the Lord from me to ſpeak unto thee?</hi> thus doth he preſumtiouſly lift himſelfe up above what he is; but I ſhall wave what might be further ſaid on this ſubject, not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to write much, but onely to give an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent demonſtration in brief of what may ſet him forth to be as he is a deceiver, and not as he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends a Saviour: and to that end I come unto the Fourth argument or evidence that he is under a ſpirit of ſedition and hereſie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:118742:16"/>
               <head>The fourth evidence which plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares he is under a ſpirit not Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine but Diabolical, <hi>to wit,</hi> his Blaſphemies.</head>
               <p>ANd in this order might have been inſerted ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral particulars already treated of, but that I intend no needleſs repetition of things paſt, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect this preſent juncture of time gives too large a ſubject to treat upon, and not onely for us to wonder at; but for future poſterity alſo to admire that ſo much of the Divel ſhould inhabit in a man, out of which I ſhall compleat this Chapter.</p>
               <p>Moſt blaſphemous is, and was that expreſſion, <hi>I am the Son of God, and the Son of God is but one;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, p.</hi> 14. 15, 16, 17</note> and the like I am ſaith he, <hi>the prophet of the moſt high God, I am the Son of God, and the everlaſting righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe is wrought in me:</hi> and then arrogantly as imitating Chriſt, he blaſphemouſly applyeth the words to himſelf, <hi>if ye had known the Father, ye would have known me alſo;</hi> and as he gives theſe teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of blaſphemy of himſelf, and is thereby guilty of blaſphemy; ſo alſo in reſpect that he receiveth titles from others which are as bad as when they call him <hi>King of Iſrael,</hi> he anſwers to it, ſee Mr.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118742:16"/>
                  <hi>Farmer</hi>'s <hi>Satan enthron'd, &amp;c.</hi> When he was aſked <hi>art thou the unſpotted Lamb of God that takeſt away the ſins of the world?</hi> he anſwers in the affirmative, <hi>Were I not a Lamb, Wolves would not ſeek to devoure me:</hi> thus taking to himſelfe the titles and attributes onely belonging to Chriſt, therein robbing God of his glory and honour. And thoſe Proſelytes of his who are trained up by and under him, doe que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſſe nothing but what they have learnt of him, and a witneſſe to this truth, it is in that he corrects them not, but countenanceth them in their actions and expreſſions of the higheſt blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie; as <hi>thou everlaſting Son of righteouſneſs and Prince of peace: Oh how my ſoul travelleth to ſee this day which</hi> Abraham <hi>ſaw and was glad, and in the ſame letter as a ſignal of obedience to him is added<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Oh</hi> I <hi>am ready to fear as a ſervant, and to obey as a child: and again, thy name is no more to be called</hi> James <hi>but</hi> Jeſus,<note place="margin">Page 8.</note> 
                  <hi>thou King of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and thou on Son of the moſt High;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Page 13.</note> 
                  <hi>and Oh thou beloved of the Lord, the Prophet of the moſt High;</hi> and <hi>Martha Simonds</hi> (a woman for her toughe,<note place="margin">Page 4.</note> indeed better befitting a Cucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool then a ſpeaking place) doth acknowledge ſhe worſhipt him; and being aſked why ſhe did ſo, ſhe ſaid, <hi>ſhe ought ſo to do it being her duty,</hi> ſhe calls him Lord, <hi>becauſe</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>he is Lord of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Prince of peace, and anointed King of Iſrael;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Page 15. 16.</note> and <hi>Dorcas Erbury</hi> witneſſeth, <hi>that he is the onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Page 17. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>and that he is worthy of honour being the holy Lord of Iſrael,</hi> and ſhe ſaith, <hi>ſhe knows no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Saviour, and ſhe believes in him the World calls</hi> James Naylor, <hi>and that ſhe calls him the Son of God,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118742:17"/>
and ſhe is commanded to call him Lord and Maſter, and to ſerve him with much more of the like nature:</hi> which to repeat at large were tedious and unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in reſpect this is ſufficient to ſhew him guilty of the Fact for which he now hath ſuffered the greater part of his puniſhment; and what I have ſaid, I ſuppoſe is ſufficient to convince any rational ſenſible man, that the ſpirit Ruling in him is not Divine but Diabolical; and I am confident that he which ſhall read Mr. <hi>John Gilpins</hi> Book, wherein he relates how he was ſeduced by the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel (yet with a Quakers pretences of a more pure and cleer light even Chriſt himſelf) who poſſeſſed him immediately and really four ſeveral times; and ſhall read this relation of <hi>Naylor</hi>'s call into this ſect, will find ſuch a concurrence in the manner that the difference will reſt onely here, the ſubject is not <hi>Gilpin</hi> but <hi>Naylor;</hi> and as the manner was alike, ſo is the matter, both being deluſions vail'd under glorious pretences of divine revelation: there extaſies were both of alike ſtrain after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the working of Satan by their own reports; onely one is ſeired in impudence, the other ſalved with repentance: but one paſſage in that of <hi>Gilpin</hi> I cannot omit willingly, which is this.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:118742:17"/>
               <head>A Remarkable paſſage and worthy your Obſervation.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GIlpin</hi> having but once taſted of that bitter berry of Apoſtacy from the truth, yet wanting that inward evidence from an internal light which others boaſted of, could not be contented to weigh but preſſed forwards from the ſhallow ſide to the bottomleſs channel of ſoul impoveriſhing errors: and therefore extremely thirſted after the act of quakeing, thinking that then he ſhould feel that internal power that might evidence their external preaching, which as yet he could not doe: But when the Divel had ſo fair an opportunity as this to enlarge his Dominion, he caſt him into that action he ſo much deſired. When the Divel as it afterwards appeared and confeſſed it ſelf to be <hi>in the likeneſs of a Dove, deſcended upon him, and entred into him, pretending to be the holy Ghoſt:</hi> in this ſtate he going to their meetings where one <hi>Chriſtopher Atkinſon</hi> was ſpeaking, he returned home with great joy in that the power (as he ſaith) which was within him had enabled him to witneſſe to what was ſaid, ſo that it may eaſily be diſcerned what that power is, whoſe doctrine the Divel bears a witneſſe unto; I am cleerly of this opinion that Satan cannot witneſſe unto the things of God
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118742:18"/>
really, but to overthrow them further by his chief policie.</p>
               <p>I come now to what I would willingly be brief in, which is to ſpeak a word or two to the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and explaining of the politique deſignes of <hi>this man of ſin James Naylor,</hi> in the carryiny on this blaſphemy, and high treaſon againſt the moſt high God of Heaven and Earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:118742:18"/>
               <head>The Politique deceits of this ſeducing Sophiſter in carrying on this his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne of Blaſphemy and Treaſon againſt God.</head>
               <p>ANd in ſo doing I ſhall firſt of all obſerve two or three things and that but name them.</p>
               <p>And the firſt is, that it was his uſual cuſtome and common doctrine both to act and to teach that it was unlawful, nay ſinful to give or receive civilities, <hi>good morrow or good deen,</hi> or <hi>you are wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come;</hi> or <hi>fare you well;</hi> nay not from children to their Parents, or inferiours to their Magiſtrates in general. And next more particularly, he not only forbid it to his hearers, but upbraided others that received titles of honour or reſpects, as <hi>Sir</hi> and the like: and in my <hi>Publique diſcovery in his</hi> 14. <hi>queries</hi> to me, and to ſeveral others he renders this as an invective againſt the Miniſters, and as a ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal token of a <hi>falſe Prophet,</hi> who ſtand praying in their Synagogue (but he cannot ſay the <hi>Pillory</hi>) and being called <hi>Maſters, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And laſtly, What he upbraided as blameable in others he now cries up not only as vertuous, but as a fruit of the immortal ſeed in himſelf, <hi>being called not only Maſter</hi> but <hi>Lord;</hi> and not Lord onely nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118742:19"/>
but <hi>King of righteouſneſs and Prince of peace:</hi> See <hi>Satan enthron'd,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 13. are theſe words, <hi>thou King of Iſrael, and Son of the moſt High<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> And ſee <hi>Mr.Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi>'s <hi>Satan enthron'd, &amp;c. p.</hi> 7. are theſe words; <hi>Oh thou faireſt amongſt ten thouſand, thou only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Son of God, how my heart painteth after thee: Oh ſtay me with Flagons and comfort me with Wine,</hi> and the like, which they doe not onely in publique but in common too, as <hi>Timothy Wedlock</hi> teſtifyeth; See Mr. <hi>Farmer</hi>'s <hi>Satan enthron'd, &amp;c. page</hi> 17. you may diſcern the hypocriſie of this deceiver that will practiſe contrary to his own doctrine, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing not onely the civilities of <hi>Maſter,</hi> but ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour as <hi>Lord;</hi> and not onely honour as <hi>Lord,</hi> but worſhip as <hi>Chriſt</hi> alſo. I ſhall now having ſpoke ſomewhat to this, alſo proceed to relate one Story which I had from a hand of repute; which was this.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:118742:19"/>
               <head>An obſervable ſtory, (and yet very true) of one <hi>Duesbury</hi> (an eminent <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> in this Land) how he lay with one <hi>Rebekah Burnhil,</hi> who he or <hi>Naylor,</hi> or ſome of their grandees had ſeduced to their Hereſie.</head>
               <p>A Friend of mine, who is a zealous friend to the truth, and an ingenuous oppoſer of their Hereſie, had by his induſtrious care procured a relation under the hand of a <hi>Lincolnſhire</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, named Mr. <hi>White,</hi> how that <hi>Duesbury</hi> (a known Seducer too, and Preacher of this Quaking here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie) having inticed a ſilly woman, named <hi>Rebekah Burnhill</hi> to his ſedition, he then indeavoured to pull her one ſtep neerer to deſtruction by multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying ſin to iniquity, and ſo as he had drawn her to his hereſie he indeavoured to intice her to his luſt, which ſhe reſiſting, and he perſuing, ſhe ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted him with this queſtion, <hi>How could he in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſo much wrong his Wife, as to lie with any other woman if he might? and what did he thinks ſhe would ſay to it ſhe knew it?</hi> He anſwered, <hi>I do her no wrong at all, in that I freely give her the ſame liberty I take my ſelf;</hi> (that was freely to be a Whore, as
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118742:20"/>
he was a Whoremaſter) whereupon in a ſhort ſpace he obtained his deſire; and having ſatisfied his luſt, ſhe propoſed another queſtion to him.</p>
               <p>Rebekah. Qu. <hi>What if I ſhould then by you prove with child? what ſhould I then do?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Duesb. An.</hi> Why then you muſt be content to be numbred amongſt the tranſgreſſors, and to make your grave with the wicked; and what a pure Saint this was I leave it to any impartial Reader to judge, that knowing the event, would againſt knowledge and that light he calls pure, commit ſin: with which we ſhould deal as did <hi>Joab</hi> with <hi>Abſolom,</hi> not ſpare it for its beauty or any thing dilectable in it, but pierce it to the heart; and that by three darts,</p>
               <p>The firſt, Repentance for ſin.</p>
               <p>The ſecond, Abſtenance from ſin.</p>
               <p>The third, Reſolution againſt ſin.</p>
               <p>But to our purpoſe, The ſaid <hi>Rebekah Burnhill</hi> afterwards repenting of her offence, and as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailing her ſin, confeſſed to the ſaid Mr. <hi>White</hi> what I have here preſented. And further, that <hi>James Naylor</hi> did attempt the ſame inconſtancy, but ſhe denied him; and <hi>Naylor</hi> hath been known to ſay, that he could as willingly and freely lie with one <hi>Rebekah</hi> as with his own Wife: on which words Mr. <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> propounded this queſtion to <hi>Naylor</hi> in the common meeting place.</p>
               <p>Q. James Naylor, <hi>What Rebekah did you mean, when you ſaid you could as willingly, as freely, and as lawfully lie with one</hi> Rebekah <hi>as with your owne Wife?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:118742:20"/>He pauſed a little, and then ſaid,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There be more <hi>Rebekahs</hi> then one in the world.</p>
               <p>To which was replied,</p>
               <p>Rep. <hi>That there are more</hi> Rebekahs <hi>then one, is nothing to the queſtion propounded; therefore we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to reſolved not how many</hi> Rebekahs <hi>there be,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1.21.22, 23, 24, 25</note> 
                  <hi>but which</hi> Rebekah <hi>you could ſo willingly lie with?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 22.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But when he ſaw that he could not avoid the queſtion,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.5, 8, 9.</note> he became ſilent.</p>
               <p>So Mr. <hi>Perſival</hi> made uſe of this as an argument at that preſent of <hi>Naylors</hi> guilt in this particular, and ſaid to the people, You may obſerve that as to the thing whereof <hi>Naylor</hi> is now accuſed, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, or at leaſt doth ſay nothing to clear himſelf of it, but according to his cuſtome indeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to avoid the queſtions. And truly to me it appears that the chief cauſe of his ſilence was not being able either to deny or confute what he was accuſed for, leſt in ſo attempting to do the thing might have been aggravated according to its proper nature, tolerating ſin; and ſince all his impudence afforded him not a confidence to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face this truth, its unqueſtionable true, elſe he would not have ſpared tongue to have rayled and lyed too if that would have done it.</p>
               <p>And here I cannot but pauſe upon and indeed admire the ſeared impudence of this arch Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, in that paſſage between him and Mr. <hi>Ives;</hi> when <hi>Naylor</hi> (that pretends to abhor diſtinctions of perſons except they may acrue to his advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage) was in diſcourſe with Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> about Chriſt's
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118742:21"/>
being born after the fleſh, or according to the fleſh; <hi>Naylor</hi> made a vaſt diſtinction between theſe two expreſſions, after the fleſh and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fleſh: But Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> proved from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture a concurrance and ſo no difference between them; which diſpute with other things he inſerts in Print, in anſwer whereunto <hi>Naylor</hi> falſly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts that Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> makes no diſtinction between being born after the fleſh and after the ſpirit. This paſſage I can witneſſe true, becauſe I read it; and truly ſince it is a matter which may ſeem a myſtery to ſome what his intent ſhould be in thus doing, ſince it muſt needs redound to his diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement when the deceit is diſcovered; I ſhall give you my thoughts of it, it being a principle amongſt them to receive what their leaders lay down or write as infallible truth; and that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is made publique by them, they all will peruſe, he did it to confirm them to himſelf, that are ſeduced by him, by making and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting them as odious as may be, that in any ways oppoſe or withſtand his hereſies; and that this is common with him, who ſo reads my <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Diſcovery</hi> and his pretended anſwer cannot but witneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:118742:21"/>
               <head>The manner how <hi>James Naylor</hi> was burned, firſt through the tongue, and afterwards branded in the forehead with the letter <hi>B.</hi> at the Royal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, London.</head>
               <p>THe relation of his former juſtly deſerved puniſhment. As firſt, Standing on the Pillory at the Pallace-yard <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and whipping from thence to the Royal Exchange, <hi>London</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been heretofore largely related by ſome who have noiſed it through the Land, I ſhall not ſo much as mind it, but paſſe it over, and come to ſpeak to that which laſt he underwent with much Impudence.</p>
               <p>On <hi>Saturday December</hi> the 27th. about 11. of the clock he was in a Coach conveyed from the common Goal of <hi>Newgate</hi> to the Black Boy neer to the Royal Exchange, <hi>London;</hi> in which houſe he continued till the Clock had ſtruck twelve at noon, when by divers on foot with Holberts, he was guarded to the Pillory, where when he came they preſently put his head into the ſame, and having pinned it down, came up <hi>Martha Symonds,</hi> and with her two others, who was ſaid to be <hi>Hannah Stranger</hi> and <hi>Dorcas Erbury;</hi> the firſt ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her ſelf juſt behind him on the right ſide, the two latter before him, the one on the right hand, the other on the left, juſt at his feet, in imitation
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:118742:22"/>
of <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> the Mother of Jeſus, and <hi>Mary</hi> the Mother of <hi>Cleophas, John</hi> 19.25. thereby to witneſſe their ſtill blaſphemous and preſumptious and heretical adoration of him, as Jeſus the Chriſt, as is more evidently expreſt by that act of <hi>Robert Rich,</hi> whom I ſaw ſtick up a paper over his head, in which it is ſaid was writ, <hi>This is the King of the Jews;</hi> word by word with that in <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.38. which plainly fulfills the words of our true Saviour, <hi>Falſe chriſts muſt come, and falſe prophets ſhall ariſe;</hi> and then he gives us this ſignal whereby we ſhould know them when they come, who ſhall ſay, <hi>loe here, and loe there is Chriſt,</hi> as do theſe: Since then we ſee the propheſie ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, let us obey the command alſo; <hi>believe them not.</hi> This I ſpeak by the way, to imploy that ſpace of time between his firſt coming and his ſufferings; for when he had ſtood juſt one hour and three quarters, they took him forth of the Pillory, and having bound him faſt with his back to the ſame, the Executioner pulled off his Cap, and having hood wink't his face &amp; taken faſt hold of his tongue, with a red hot Iron he bored a hole quite thorow; which having done, and pulling the cloth off that covered his face, he put a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerchief over his eyes, and ſo putting his left hand in his pole, he taking the red hot Iron-letter in his other hand, put it to his forehead, which gave a little flaſh of ſmoak; which being done, <hi>Rich</hi> licked the ſame, as did the dogs the wounds of <hi>Lazarus;</hi> and then ſang, which he did often before, both ſtroaking and kiſſing him, which he
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:118742:22"/>
ſuffered with an admired impudence; ſo <hi>Naylor</hi> was firſt conveyed back to the Black-boy, and thence again to <hi>Newgate,</hi> where he reſts till he ſets forward to ſuffer deſerved ſhame in like manner at <hi>Briſtoll.</hi> What I have ſaid in this, I ſaw and therefore can witneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:118742:23"/>
               <head>I ſhall now proceed to lay down ſome of their wicked and erroneous Tenets not held out to my knowledge by any one man; but by them all in General.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. They deny diſtinction of the perſons in the God-head; ſee <hi>Fox</hi>'s <hi>Sauls errant to Damaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> p. 18. there he affirms, that it <hi>ſhews only a buſie mind to enquire whether there be any individual God diſtinguiſhed into the Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. They hold the holy Scriptures, <hi>to wit,</hi> the writings of the <hi>Prophets, Evangeliſts and Apoſtles as not being the Word of God, but ſome of them call it carnal, and all of them a dead letter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. They deny any Expoſition except ſuch as they themſelves make, and call expounding, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juration; and he that takes a Text to expound it, they ſay is a <hi>Conjurer.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. They hold their own licentious and erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous writings and ſpeakings to be equal with the written Word of God: and <hi>George Fox</hi> ſaid to <hi>Joſ. Killet</hi> that it was all one and the ſame to take a Text <hi>out of his writings and</hi> Paul<hi>'s Epiſtles,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">See the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of a <hi>Treacherous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, &amp;c. p.</hi> 5.</note> 
                     <hi>and to preach upon it:</hi> this is an evidence by what ſpirit theſe men are under.<note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Bourn,</hi> p. 22.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. They hold that Jeſus Chriſt is come into their fleſh, that the man Chriſt dwels in them, and that he is ſavingly in all men, <hi>even Turks and Infidels,</hi> but that in them he is held under corruption.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:118742:23"/>6. They deny the <hi>Aſcenſion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7. Some deny the <hi>Reſurrection.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Saints errand to <hi>Damaſcup, p.</hi> 57.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>8. They diſown Chriſts imputative <hi>righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and depend <hi>upon that which is inherent in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>9. They hold that in <hi>Regeneration</hi> there is <hi>no new matter, no habit of grace or ſeed of God infuſed; but that Chriſt that was in man before, is then onely raiſed up in them out of Priſon, and from under corruption.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>10. They hold the full enjoyment of preſent <hi>purity</hi> and <hi>immortality,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">See my <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, &amp;c..</hi>
                     </note> as who ſo reads my <hi>Publique Diſcovery</hi> may find it cleerly proved, <hi>with fulneſs of glory that they enjoy God, Chriſt, the Reſurrection, Judgement, and all they look for they enjoy here in this life, not expecting any other World or Kingdome, but deny any local Heaven or Hell.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>12. They hold <hi>that they neither do nor can ſin.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>13. They hold that to pray that our ſins may be forgiven, <hi>is needleſs;</hi> and to aſk any thing of God, <hi>is folly; for he knows our wants.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>14. They deny all <hi>Ordinances,</hi> and concerning Prayer, Preaching, the Sacraments, &amp;c. <hi>Fox</hi> ſaid, <hi>away with them for he denyed them all:</hi> And I heard <hi>Edward Borowes</hi> ſay, <hi>that they were an abomination to the Lord,</hi> with much more of the like nature. But think not that I ſhall accuſe any one man as hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all theſe, but onely that amongſt them this they believe, ſome in a leſſer and ſome in a greater meaſure. I ſhall only make mention of ſome abſurd actions and opinions practiſed and upheld amongſt them that now are and were of their ſociety in general.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:118742:24"/>
               <head>A brief Narrative of ſome very Remarkable paſſages and abſurdities committed by and amongſt that heretical Sect of Quakers.</head>
               <p>ANd whereas <hi>Chriſtopher Atkinſon</hi> was once as famous as moſt that now ſtand with and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, I ſhall in a word give you to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that laſt Spring at a Seſſions held at <hi>Norwich,</hi> he the ſaid <hi>Atkinſon</hi> was indited, arraigned and found guilty of adultery, and then confeſſed the Fact, and ſince hath left their ſociety, and lives ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villy with his Wife in the ſaid City, as a Letter I once ſaw from thence teſtifyed to be true: this <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinſon</hi> was once adored rather as an Angel then reſpected as a man amongſt them: But it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that he was rotten at the Core, and his heart was not found.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>George Fox</hi> before ſufficient witneſs,<note place="margin">See the <hi>Perfect Phariſee, p.</hi> 3.</note> as Doctor <hi>Marſhall, Col. Weſt</hi> and one Mr. <hi>Sawro,</hi> ſaid, that he was equal with God himſelf;<note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Bourn</hi>'s <hi>Defence of the Scriptures, p.</hi> 90.</note> ſee <hi>the relation of the Northern Quakers, p.</hi> 2. who alſo ſaid, <hi>he was the eternal Judge of the World,</hi> as <hi>George Beket, Adam Sands</hi> teſtifyeth, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>He hath alſo avowed himſelf to be the <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>George Beket</hi> and <hi>Iſaac Bourn</hi> affirmeth, ſee the ſame Author, <hi>p.</hi> 3. ſo did <hi>James Naylor</hi> ſay alſo, <hi>that he was God and Chriſt,</hi> as teſtifyeth three witneſſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:118742:24"/>
               <head>Here followeth a ſtory no leſſe ſtrange then true, though the ſtrangeneſſe of it may render it ſome what incredible; which is as followeth,</head>
               <p>LAſt Spring, or thereabouts, were met together in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> about an hundered and ſix ſcore men, women and children, of all ages and ſects except ſucking babes, about eight a clock in the evening, where they continued their uſuall diſcourſe till about eleven of the clock at night;<note place="margin">Rom. 2.22, 23, 24.</note> and when their ſpeaker had done his rable, they all very lovingly (like ſwine in a ſtye) went to bed together in the ſtraw ſtark naked, ſave what men and women were in beds. An act not becoming Chriſtians, but rather Infidels. This was often times (in my hearing) offered to be proved in their publique meeting place, but they never durſt put it to trial. And but a little before that there were (as I was informed for a certain truth) ſome of this factious hereſie preſumed ſo far on their deluſions, that they ſlew a child, preſuming to raiſe it from the dead; which when they ſaw they could not accompliſh, they were apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and at the Sizes condemned and executed for the ſaid murder.</p>
               <p>Not much unlike this was that bold peremptory part of <hi>George Fox,</hi> who neer <hi>Kendal</hi> commanded a cripple to caſt away his crutches and walk, which he did, but remained a cripple ſtill; and <hi>Fox</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:118742:25"/>
wrought his own diſparagement, ſee the <hi>irreligion of the Northern Quakers, p.</hi> 29. Many more be the abſurdities that I could name of this like nature, but I ſhall only inſtance two or three in brief.</p>
               <p>A man came ſtark naked to the Market-croſſe in <hi>Kertby-more,</hi> and there ſtood ſpeaking in that poſture to the people, with this excuſe, <hi>That he ſtood naked by the command of the ſpirit, that he might ſpeak the naked truth;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">What father that was (whether of of truth or of lies) the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates. on demon.</note> witneſſe Mr. <hi>George Emot</hi> in his <hi>Northern blaſt,</hi> about <hi>p.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Whyton,</hi> a place alſo in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> a woman of this quaking ſect, came naked from her own bed to another womans huſband, a companion &amp; of her own ſect, and bid him open his bed, for the <hi>Father</hi>* had ſent her unto him;<note place="margin">See the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riers and Quakers caſe at the ſecond hearing is no lie, p.</note> the man had at that time another man in bed with him, he roſe to give place to this woman, and left this ſerious couple to lie together, according to the womans revelations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:118742:25"/>
               <head>A moſt Remarkable Story yet very true, of that mad, blind and preſumptuous ſpirit in them.</head>
               <p>ONe <hi>Miſtris Williamſon</hi> at <hi>Appleby</hi> moſt ſenſleſly affirmed in the hearing of divers, <hi>that ſhe was the eternal Son of God,</hi> to which ſome preſently Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, that ſhe was a woman; and therefore could not be <hi>the eternal Son of God:</hi> to which ſhe boldly replyed, <hi>no, you are all women, but I am a man.</hi> By this may eaſily reſolved how abſurd, <hi>non</hi>-ſenſical and arogant that ſpirit in them is, that tranſports them ſo far as to impoſſibilities.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:118742:26"/>
               <head>As peremptory a paſſage almoſt is that if not as blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous of <hi>Edward Burrows</hi> in a Letter of his from <hi>Waterford</hi> in <hi>Ireland;</hi> in which are theſe words,</head>
               <p>I <hi>live ſaith he, in a Land where the Divel rules Lords and Kings, but I am reſerved in eternal power and glory, and righteouſneſs over all to reign for ever.</hi> And to reigne over all in that ſenſe, can be none under Chriſt; for of him the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>that when he is ſaid to have all things made ſubject unto him; yet God that ſubjecteth all is excepted:</hi> and if we favour him ſo much in conſtruction as to exempt the Father, its evident he aſſumes the place of the Son; which to doe, is blaſphemy: And little leſs is that boldneſs of the ſame Seducer when he ſetteth this expreſſion to his Pamphlet, <hi>Sealed by the eternal ſpirit of God:</hi> which expreſſion of his if ſeriouſly conſidered, little cauſe had ſome perſons not now mean in Authority ſo much to juſtifie that grand ſeducer <hi>James Naylor,</hi> as to ſay, (though unjuſtly) <hi>his accuſations were rather of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice then matter of fact.</hi> If he or they that ſo ſaid would but weigh what back-friends, not onely <hi>Naylor</hi> but all their Sect are in general to them; becauſe they deny authority; but in particular in that here <hi>Borowes</hi> ſaith, <hi>he lives in a Land where the Divel</hi> (not God) <hi>rules Lords and Kings:</hi> when que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſs
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:118742:26"/>
by the latter is meant, his Highneſſe, but that he dares not ſpeak out: as more plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by that of <hi>Francis Howgal</hi> in the North, who told one Mr. <hi>Burton</hi> a Magiſtrate there, <hi>that the Law</hi> (ſaid <hi>Howgal</hi>) <hi>by which thou acteſt, is Tyranny and Oppreſſion.</hi> And if the Law be Tyranny, What then (by his account) is the Law-maker &amp; maintainer but a Tyrant? I hope the ſupreme Authority will take their own honour and ſafety into ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration with the glory of Chriſt and his Goſpel, which is deeply intereſted in this buſineſs.</p>
               <p>And a ſtrong witneſſe of the unſanctity of their ſpirit, is their unſtability; for God is unchangeable, <hi>for he changes not;</hi> and as is he, ſo is his ſpirit: and that theirs is no ſtable but mutable one is evident in that a man in the North in a town called <hi>Kerby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanſdale</hi> that had been of their ſociety, a good while falling ſick of an Ague, of which being kept in a moneth, &amp; being recovered went to their meeting again, he profeſſed he found them ſo much altered in their Judgements and Principles in that time, that he could onely by their faces, but not by their Principles know them to be the ſame men.</p>
               <p>And one Mr. <hi>Geor. Emot</hi> in his <hi>Northern blaſt, p.</hi> 6. ingeniouſly confeſſeth, that ſince he left them and returned to his right ſenſes, (he teſtifyeth who had tried the experience) that though (whilſt he was a Quaker) he thought himſelf to be all light; he knew nothing really (but imaginary) but what he knew before, and had learned of the Miniſters.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:118742:27"/>And as ſtability is an evidence of the ſpirit of godlyneſs, as witneſſeth that of <hi>Jude</hi> concerning <hi>Michael</hi>'s Diſputation with the Divel about the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> he durſt offer neither violence of words or deeds further, then <hi>the Lord reward thee,</hi> and this I have heard them preach (if their confuſed nonſenſical prating may be ſo tearmed) but I never knew them practice it, and therefore to me their unbridled and libertaine-like words and actions, is an evidence that if their ſpirit be infallible as they pretend, its not impiety but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; and ſince God and Chriſt, and their ſpirit is meekneſſe, joy, peace and love, what is contrary (as violent diſcourſe but turbulent and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) is not of God, but in oppoſition to him; and ſince the ſpirit in <hi>Naylor,</hi> and the other of his Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, is ſuch a ſpirit, its cleer they are not of God or goodneſſe.</p>
               <p>And to demonſtrate this is ſo eaſie that ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities of matter for proof makes mee pauſe which to inſert and which to omit; therefore I ſhall only make uſe of what hath paſſed between them and me, or but little elſe.</p>
               <p>One time being at the Bull and Mouth, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by chance the day before ſeen a ſheet of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted paper containing there informations given in upon oath proving that one <hi>Borows</hi> &amp; <hi>Howgall,</hi> and chiefly one <hi>Hoberthorn</hi> had bewitched or inchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Mary White</hi> to death; which having about me at that time, after ſome diſcourſe had with him, that then and at that time there ſpoke (who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I never ſaw) I produced this ſheet, and ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:118742:27"/>
on a place with my feet about a ſtory from the ground, I went to read, and in ſome places to comment upon it, the Quakers by violence pluckt me down by the legs, when (had not Gods preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance been ſtronger then the Divell and their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, I might have been in danger of death; but God in mercy preſerved me that I had no hurt.</p>
               <p>The party then ſpeaking was <hi>Richard Hobber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorn,</hi> who though he heard himſelfe ſo much in queſtion, and I often asked him his name, yet hee would neither confeſs nor deny it, or ſay any thing to the clearing the matter of fact.</p>
               <p>They call'd me then dog, ſerpent, and divel, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>An other time one of their mankind women puld a lock of hair from off my head in their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety in a great quantity, with ſeveral blows and thruſts; with curſings and judgements I thinke innumerable.</p>
               <p>But I wonder the leſſe at this, in reſpect Mr. <hi>Bourn</hi> in his <hi>Defence of the Scriptures,</hi> in the Epiſtle Dedicatory, he teſtifies that a Quaker told him that his houſe was formerly plunder'd but ere long ſhould be pulled down about his ears.</p>
               <p>And in <hi>Gloceſterſhire,</hi> the Quakers making a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance at the burial of an Inhabitant of <hi>Paneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> in the ſaid County, and going to offer vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence or at leaſt uncivilities to the Miniſter at the grave, and one Mr. <hi>R. P.</hi> a known honeſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, then high Conſtable, doing his duty to keep
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:118742:28"/>
the pence: a Quaker then preſently ſtrikes the ſaid Officer over the ſide of the head ſo violently, that he received much dammage. This I am ſure is a truth.</p>
               <p>Much more I might ſpeake, and have truth my protector; but I had rather be ſparing then to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:118742:28"/>
               <head>A very evidential paſſage of that luna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick and unparaleld ſpirit that ruleth in them, as how like men diſtracted they run along the Streets in a ſtrange manner.</head>
               <p>ON Sunday laſt, being <hi>December</hi> the 28th. about two or three of the clock in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, ſome <hi>Quakers</hi> being met together at the ſign of the Roſe in the new market-place <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> where <hi>Martha Symons</hi> and the other two Siſters in iniquity are in cuſtody, of a ſuddain that ſpirit in them moved them to fall a ſinging their titular ſongs of <hi>Sion,</hi> as they call them, and daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing a while till on the ſuddain they ran down ſtairs and forth of doors, and ſo down the Strand, and <hi>Fleetſtreet</hi> to the Royal Exchange, <hi>London</hi> crying and proclaiming fire and vengeance againſt <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the ſword of the Lords wrath was drawn againſt this great and wicked City, where one <hi>I. B.</hi> a now profeſſed <hi>Quaker,</hi> meeting with them, asked them the matter, who replied the word of the Lord was gone forth, I ſaid he, I know that long ſince it went forth, but what was the cauſe they run in that unwonted manner, or words to this effect, they ſaid that the vengeance and fire of the Lords wrath was poured forth againſt this City, and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> muſt come to judgement, who
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118742:29"/>
being ſince aſked ſeriouſly what he thought of them, ſaith he really believes they are either mad or bewitched, ſome of them ran without hats, ſome without clokes, ſome without either. What to term this ſtrange and unheard of ſort of men, is ſuch a myſtery to me, as I know better how to admire at then expreſſe; and therefore leave it to the ingenuous Reader to determine.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
